Guide to the Alfredo de Palchi and Sona Raiziss papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alfredo de Palchi and Sona Raiziss papers
1920-2005
1990-2005
GEN MSS 947
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18.4
(49 boxes)
The Alfredo de Palchi and Sona Raiziss Papers contain correspondence between de Palchi and Raiziss and with others, concerning their writings, the literary journal Chelsea, and literary prizes; poems, other writings, and English translations of Italian poetry by de Palchi and Raiziss; writings by others, mostly Italian poetry translated into English by Raiziss and de Palchi, published by them in Chelsea, or submitted for literary prizes sponsored by them; clippings and other printed material relating to writings of de Palchi and Raiziss, and to other poets; biographical information about Raiziss and scrapbooks of ephemera relating to her early life and education at the University of Pennsylvania and Cornell University, 1920s; a few audiocassettes and videocassettes relating to poets and poetry readings; and a small amount of photographs and drawings. Research strengths include poetry by de Palchi and Raiziss; translation of Italian poetry into English by them and others; their editorship of Chelsea; other 20th-century Italian poets and their translators; the Academy of American Poets and the Raiziss/de Palchi Fellowship; and the Bordighera Poetry Prize.
De Palchi, Alfredo, 1926-
Raiziss, Sona
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alfredo de Palchi, 1997-2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 47 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 48 (reel-to-reel tape): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 49 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Chelsea Records (GEN MSS 1090)
Alfredo de Palchi (1926-)
Italian poet and translator. De Palchi was born in Italy and emigrated to the United States, settling in New York City in 1956. In 1952 he married poet and translator Sona Raiziss, with whom he edited the the literary journal Chelsea, 1966-1994. After Raiziss's death in 1994, de Palchi edited Chelsea, 1994-2007, and has continued to manage the Sonia Raiziss Giop Charitable Foundation. He married Rita di Pace in 1989. Chelsea Editions, a subdivision of Chelsea Associates, edited by de Palchi, publishes bilingual editions of literature, mostly contemporary Italian poetry with English translation.
Sona Raiziss (1909-1994)
American poet and translator, also spelled Sonia Raiziss. Raiziss was born in Germany, was raised in Philadelphia, and attended the University of Pennsylvania, Cornell University, and Columbia University. Her translations include poetry of Alfredo de Palchi, whom she married in 1952. With de Palchi, she edited the literary journal Chelsea, 1966-1994. Raiziss founded the Sonia Raiziss Giop Charitable Foundation, which continues to fund the Jane Austen Essay Contest, the Bordighera Poetry Prize, and the Raiziss/de Palchi Translation Awards.
Scope and Contents
The Alfredo de Palchi and Sona Raiziss Papers contain correspondence between de Palchi and Raiziss and with others, concerning their writings, the literary journal Chelsea, and literary prizes; poems, other writings, and English translations of Italian poetry by de Palchi and Raiziss; writings by others, mostly Italian poetry translated into English by Raiziss and de Palchi, published by them in Chelsea, or submitted for literary prizes sponsored by them; clippings and other printed material relating to writings of de Palchi and Raiziss, and to other poets; biographical information about Raiziss and scrapbooks of ephemera relating to her early life and education at the University of Pennsylvania and Cornell University, 1920s; a few audiocassettes and videocassettes relating to poets and poetry readings; and a small amount of photographs and drawings. Research strengths include poetry by de Palchi and Raiziss; translation of Italian poetry into English by them and others; their editorship of Chelsea; other 20th-century Italian poets and their translators; the Academy of American Poets and the Raiziss/de Palchi Fellowship; and the Bordighera Poetry Prize.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1961-2005. II. Writings, 1930s-1999. III. Writings by Others, 1939-2003. IV. Printed Material, 1930s-1950s. V. Other Papers, 1920s-1930s.
Chelsea (New York, N.Y.); American poetry -- 20th Century; Italian poetry -- 20th Century -- Translations into English; Italian poetry -- 21st century -- Translations into English; Literary prizes -- United States; Little magazines -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, Italian -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, Italian -- 21st century -- Archives; Women poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Born digital -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Scrapbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Sound recordings -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- Italy -- 20th Century; Poets -- Italy -- 21st century; De Palchi, Alfredo, 1926-; De Palchi, Alfredo, 1926- -- Translations into English; Raiziss, Sona; Academy of American Poets; Cornell University -- Students; University of Pennsylvania -- Students
- Correspondence, 1961-2005; Series I; 5.84; (14 boxes)
  Related Archival Materials note
  Additional correspondence is in Series II, Writings, and Series III, Writings of Others.
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Sona Raiziss; and Alfredo de Palchi. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, followed by unsorted correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence includes letters concerning writings of de Palchi and Raiziss, literary prizes managed by them, writings of others, and Chelsea. Some letters enclose drafts of writings or photographs. Unsorted correspondence may include additional letters from correspondents who are individually listed.
  - Sona Raiziss
    - de Palchi, Alfredo, 1966 July-August (Box 1)
    - Unsorted, 10 (Box 1)
    - Unsorted, 11 (Box 2)
    - Unsorted, 12 (Box 3)
    - Unsorted, 13 (Box 4)
    - Unsorted, 10 (Box 5)
  - Alfredo de Palchi
    - Academy of American Poets, 1994-2002; 4 (Box 5)
      About the Raiziss/de Palchi Fellowship
    - Academy of American Poets, 1994-2002; 17 (Box 6)
    - Academy of American Poets, 1994-2002; 16 (Box 7)
    - American Association for Italian Studies, 1998 (Box 7)
    - BOA Editions, 1997, 1999; 2 (Box 8)
    - Bordighera Press, 2001 (Box 8)
    - Bressan, Michela, 1997-1998 (Box 8)
    - Buffoni, Franco, 1996-1997 (Box 8)
    - Byrne, Elena Karina, 2003; 2 (Box 8)
    - Farina, Raymond, 1997-2000; 3 (Box 8)
    - Gioseffi, Daniela, 5 (Box 8)
      About the Bordighera Poetry Prize
    - Gioseffi, Daniela, 2 (Box 9)
    - Italian Poetry Society of America, 1996-1997 (Box 9)
    - Lawner, Lynne, 3 (Box 9)
    - Live Poets Society (Box 9)
    - Marangoni, Marco, 1992, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Pasanisi, Roberto, 1996-1997 (Box 9)
    - Piazza Nicolai, Adeodato, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Raiziss, Sona, circa 1961-1965; 4 (Box 9)
    - Società operaia di mutuo soccorso ed istruzione San Vito al Tagliamento, 2 (Box 9)
    - Stortoni, Laura Anna, 1997 (Box 10)
    - Vettori, Alessandro, 1997 (Box 10)
    - Westermann, Barbara, 1997-1999, undated; 3 (Box 10)
    - Wilentz, Ted, 1997; 5 (Box 10)
    - Xenos Books, 1996-2002; 3 (Box 10)
    - Zollo, Vincenzo, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence removed from books, 1994-2005, undated (Box 10)
    - Unsorted, 1996-2000, undated; 15 (Box 11)
    - Unsorted, 1996-2000, undated; 14 (Box 12)
    - Unsorted, 1996-2000, undated; 16 (Box 13)
    - Unsorted, 1996-2000, undated; 17 (Box 14)
- Writings, 1930s-1999; Series II; 6.72; (17 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Sona Raiziss and Alfredo de Palchi; Sona Raiziss; and Alfredo de Palchi. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by work title or genre, followed by unsorted writings.
  Includes drafts of poetry, poetry collections, and other writings by de Palchi and Raiziss, some with related correspondence. Raiziss's writings include translations of poetry by de Palchi. The Writings by Sona Raiziss and Alfredo De Palchi subseries consists mostly of English translations of Italian poetry of other writers, some with related biographical information and correspondence. Some of these writers are also represented in Series III, Writings of Others.
  - Sona Raiziss and Alfredo de Palchi
    - Italian poetry translations and notes, 11 (Box 15)
      Includes poetry of Arnaldo di Benedetto, Vincenzo Cardarelli, Bartolo Cattafi, Eugenio Montale, Mario Novaro, Lucio Piccolo, Leonardo Sinisgalli, David Turoldo, Giuseppe Ungaretti, and others
    - Other poetry translations, 2 (Box 15)
    - Other poetry translations, 4 (Box 16)
    - Other poetry translations by Sona Raiziss and others, 2 (Box 16)
  - Sona Raiziss
    - Bucks County Blues, 8 (Box 16)
    - Bucks County Blues, 7 (Box 17)
    - Free Fall, 4 (Box 17)
    - Modern European Poetry (Bantam Books, 1978), 15 (Box 18)
      Includes translations of: Dino Campana, Giorgio Caproni, Vincenzo Cardarelli, Bartolo Cattafi, Luciano Erba, Alfonso Gatto, Eugenio Montale, Giorgio Orelli, Cesare Pavese, Lucio Piccolo, Salvatore Quasimodo, Umberto Saba, Rocco Scotellaro, Vittorio Sereni, Leonardo Sinisgalli, David Turoldo, and Giuseppe Ungaretti
    - Modern European Poetry (Bantam Books, 1978), 4 (Box 19)
    - Translations of poetry by Alfredo de Palchi, 5 (Box 19)
    - Translations of Italian poets at Spoleto, 3 (Box 19)
    - Translations of Hungarian poems, 2 (Box 20)
    - Translations, unsorted, 11 (Box 20)
    - Poems, unsorted, 10 (Box 21)
    - Poems, unsorted, 10 (Box 22)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Audiocassette: use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Sonia Raiziss introducing reading from the Italian, undated; 1; 00:37:48 (Box 49, Item barcode 39002091399288)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile material.
    - Poems, unsorted, 21 (Box 23)
    - Poems, unsorted, 12 (Box 24)
    - Other writings, unsorted, 6 (Box 25)
    - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, most by or about Sona Raiziss, 1930s-1950s (Box 31 (Oversize))
  - Alfredo de Palchi
    - Addictive Aversions. Drafts and reviews, 1999; 7 (Box 25)
    - Addictive Aversions. Drafts and reviews, 1999 (Box 26)
    - Anonymous Constellation. Translated by Sona Raiziss. Drafts, 1996-1997; 7 (Box 26)
    - Essenza carnale (Box 26)
    - Movimenti, momenti, e mutazioni. Drafts, 2 (Box 26)
    - Movimenti, momenti, e mutazioni. Drafts, 9 (Box 27)
    - The Scorpion's Dark Dance. Drafts and correspondence, 4 (Box 27)
    - The Scorpion's Dark Dance. Drafts and correspondence, 7 (Box 28)
    - Writings, unsorted, 1961-1997; 4 (Box 28)
    - Writings, unsorted, 1961-1997; 9 (Box 29)
    - Writings, unsorted, 1961-1997 (Box 30)
    - Reviews, unsorted, 3 (Box 30)
    - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, most by or about Alfredo de Palchi, 1960s (Box 31 (Oversize))
- Writings of Others, 1939-2003; Series III; 3.34; (8 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of author or subject.
  Contains writings by and about authors, translators, and visual artists, some with related correspondence. Some writings of others relate to Chelsea or to translations by Raiziss or de Palchi; additional translations may be found in Series II, Writings.
  - Allen, Beverly, undated (Box 32)
  - Allen, William, 1997 (Box 32)
  - Bertoldo Roberto. Il calvario delle gru, 2002 (Box 32)
  - Biagioni, Amelia. "The Hunts", undated (Box 32)
  - Bortolani, Ljuba Merlina, 1996-1998; 2 (Box 32)
  - Byrne, Elena Karina, 2003 (Box 32)
  - Caproni, Giorgio, 2001-2002; 4 (Box 32)
  - Carle, Barbara, 2000; 5 (Box 33)
  - Di Pasquale, Emanuel, 2000-2003, undated; 10 (Box 33)
    Includes typescript of Escapes the Night and a published copy of "Europa"
    Includes translations of poems by Roberto Bertoldo, Milo De Angelis, and Silvio Ramat
  - Di Pasquale, Emanuel, 2000-2003, undated; 8 (Box 34)
  - Erba, Luciano
    See also: Sereni, Vittorio
    - The Hippopotamus, undated (Box 34)
    - The Metaphysical Streetcar Conductor, 1998; 2 (Box 34)
    - The Metaphysical Streetcar Conductor, 1998; 6 (Box 35)
    - Other writings, 1996-1997; 3 (Box 35)
  - Greenberg, Samuel. Poems from the Greenberg Mss ., edited by James Laughlin, 1939 (Box 35)
  - Hahn, Robert, 2003 (Box 35)
  - Jackson, Laura (Riding), 1998; 2 (Box 35)
    Includes material from the Laura (Riding) Jackson Symposium held in 1998, and the Laura (Riding) Jackson Home Preservation Foundation
  - Jackson, Laura (Riding), 1998; 7 (Box 36)
    Videocassettes: use of original is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    Includes material from the Laura (Riding) Jackson Symposium held in 1998, and the Laura (Riding) Jackson Home Preservation Foundation.
  - Jackson, Laura (Riding). "To Let Be, and Let Do: Laura (Riding) Jackson in Florida." 15:12 (copy 1), 1998 October; GENMSS947_0001; 1; 00:15:55 (Box 36, Item barcode 39002102370203)
  - Jackson, Laura (Riding). "To Let Be, and Let Do: Laura (Riding) Jackson in Florida." 15:12 (copy 2), 1998 October; GENMSS947_0002; 1; This tape was not digitized. It is a duplicate. (Box 36, Item barcode 39002102370211)
  - Jackson, Laura (Riding). "A Short Sentence for Private Reflections on the Universal Length of Meaning," limited edition broadside, signed, 1995 (Box 46 (Oversize))
  - Manzoni, Alessandro. The Betrothed, 1954 (Box 37)
  - Montale, Eugenio / Sereni, Vittorio., undated; 1; 00:29:41 (Box 49, Item barcode 39002091243197)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Nalan, Felice, 1966 (Box 37)
  - OM, 1976 (Box 46 (Oversize))
  - Piccolo, Lucio, 1971-1973 (Box 37)
  - Quasimodo, Salvatore, 2001 (Box 37)
  - Ridinger, Gayle, 2002 (Box 37)
    Translation of poems by Camillo Sbarbaro
  - Sereni, Vittorio, 2002-2003, undated; 5 (Box 37)
    See also: Montale, Eugenio
  - Sereni, Vittorio / Erba, Luciano., undated; 1; 00:54:37; Static and a high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 49, Item barcode 39002091243205)
  - Sicari, Giovanna, 2003 (Box 38)
  - Snodgrass, Ann. Knowing Noise: the English Poems of Amelia Rosselli, 2 (Box 38)
  - Spencer, Theodore. The Paradox in the Circle (Box 38)
  - Ulrichs, Timm, 8 (Box 38)
  - Vitiello, Justin (Box 38)
  - Unsorted, 13 (Box 39)
- Printed Material, 1930s-1950s; Series IV; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Contains literary journals, photocopied articles, and clippings, some annotated by Raiziss or de Palchi, including materials relating to some names represented in Series III, Writings of Others. Unsorted materials may include additional writings by de Palchi and Raiziss.
  - Scrapbook of clippings related to authors, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 40)
  - Scrapbook of clippings related to poets, 1930s-1940s (Box 41)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, 1940s (Box 41)
  - Clippings, unsorted, 2 (Box 41)
    Includes clippings related to poets
  - Other printed material, unsorted, 13 (Box 42)
  - Other printed material, unsorted, 15 (Box 43)
- Other Papers, 1920s-1930s; Series V; 0.54; (3 boxes)
  - Photographs and drawings, 2 (Box 44)
  - Sona Raiziss personal papers, 3 (Box 44)
    Contains biographical information, identification cards, and school transcripts
  - Sona Raiziss scrapbook, 1920s-1930s (Box 45 (Oversize))
    Contains clippings, drawings, correspondence, and ephemera, most relating to the University of Pennsylvania and Cornell University, or to European travel
  - Sona Raiziss University of Pennsylvania diploma (Box 46 (Oversize))
- Restricted Fragile Materials, 0.29; (2 boxes)
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Computer media
    - FREE FALL 76 pp. Poems by SONIA RAIZISS Selected and Edited by Emanuel diPasquale, 2003-genm-0923-d-0001; 1 (Box 47)
      Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Coperfine -Il calvario delle gru-, 2003-genm-0604-d-0005; 1 (Box 47)
    - From Fire to Water: On the Poetry of Alfredo De Palchi Barbara Carle, 2003-genm-0604-d-0003; 1 (Box 47)
    - The calvary of the Cranes di R. Bertoldo Versone WinWord 2000 e Versone RTF, 2003-genm-0604-d-0001; 1 (Box 47)
    - The Calvary of the Cranes di R. Bertoldo Version Macintosh ([illegible] correspondere), 2003-genm-0604-d-0002; 1 (Box 47)
    - NEW AND SELECTED POEMS by Emanuel di Pasquale, 2003-genm-0604-d-0004; 1 (Box 47)
  - Montale, Eugenio / Sereni, 1961 December 3; 1; 00:29:41 (Box 48 (Oversize), Item barcode 39002091243213)